<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ielts>
<content code="ielts01">

<listening>
	<directions>
		<direction1>
			<![CDATA[Complete the notes below<br />
			Write <b><i>MORE THAN THREE WORDS AND/OR A NUMBER</i></b> for each answer.]]>
		</direction1>
		<direction2>
			<![CDATA[Complete the notes below<br />
			Write <b><i>ONE WORDS AND/OR A NUMBER</i></b> for each answer.]]>
		</direction2>
		<direction3>Choose the correct letter, A, B or C</direction3>
		<direction4><![CDATA[Choose TWO letter, A &#8211; E]]></direction4>
		<direction5>
			<![CDATA[Choose the correct letter, A, B or C<br />
			<h2>Course Feedback</h2>]]>
		</direction5>
		<direction6>
			<![CDATA[Complete the notes below.<br />
			Write <b>NO MORE THAN TWO WORDS</b> for each answer.]]>
		</direction6>
	</directions>

	<questions>
		<question id="1" multiple="0" qty="10" dir="1">
			<![CDATA[
			<h3>JOB ENQUIRY</h3><br />
			<i>Example</i><br />
			<ul><li>Work at: <u>a restaurant</u></li></ul><br />
			<ul>
				<li><b>Type of work: 1</b> <div id="ques1" class="questext"></div></li>
				<li><b>Number of hours per week:</b> 12 hours</li>
				<li><b>Would need work permit</b></li>
				<li><b>Work in the: 2</b> <div id="ques2" class="questext"></div> branch</li>
				<li><b>Nearest bus stop: next to</b><div id="ques3" class="questext"></div></li>
				<li><b>Pay: 4 &#163;</b> <div id="ques4" class="questext"></div> an hour</li>
				<li><b>Extra benefits:</b>
					<ul>
						<li>a free dinner</li>
						<li>extra pay when you work on <b>5</b> <div id="ques5" class="questext"></div></li>
						<li>transport home when you work <b>6</b> <div id="ques6" class="questext"></div></li>	
					</ul>
				</li>
				<li><b>Qualities required:</b>
					<ul>
						<li><b>7</b> <div id="ques7" class="questext"></div></li>
						<li>ability to <b>8</b> <div id="ques8" class="questext"></div></li>	
					</ul>
				</li>
				<li><b>Interview arranged for:</b> Thursday <b>9</b> <div id="ques9" class="questext"></div> at 6 p.m</li>
				<li><b>Bring the names of two referees</b></li>
				<li><b>Ask for:</b> Samira <b>10</b> <div id="ques10" class="questext"></div></li>
			</ul>
			]]>
		</question>



		<question id="11" multiple="0" qty="6" dir="2">
			<![CDATA[
			<h2>SPORTS WORLD</h2>
			<ul>
				<li>a new <b>11</b><div id="ques11"  class="questext"></div> of an international sports goods company</li>
				<li>located in the shopping centre to the <b>12</b><div id="ques12" class="questext"></div> of Bradcaster</li>
				<li>has sports <b>13</b><div id="ques13" class="questext"></div> and enquipment on floors 1 &#8211; 3</li>
				<li>can get you any item within <b>14</b><div id="ques14" class="questext"></div> days</li>
				<li>shop specialises in equipment for <b>15</b><div id="ques15" class="questext"></div></li>
				<li>has a special section which just sells <b>16</b><div id="ques16" class="questext"></div></li>
			</ul>
			]]>
		</question>
		<question id="17" multiple="1" dir="3">
			<description>A champion athlete will be in the shop</description>
			<a>on Saturday morning only.</a>
			<b>all day Saturday.</b>
			<c>for the whole weekend.</c>
		</question>
		<question id="18" multiple="1" dir="3">
			<description>The first person to answer 20 quiz questions correctly will win</description>
			<a>gym membership.</a>
			<b>a video.</b>
			<c>a calendar.</c>
		</question>
		<question id="19" multiple="2" dir="4">
			<description>Which TWO pieces of information does the speaker give about the fitness test?</description>
			<a>You need to reserve a place.</a>
			<b>It is free to account holders.</b>
			<c>You get advice on how to improve your health.</c>
			<d>It takes place in a special clinic.</d>
			<e>It is cheaper this month.</e>
		</question>

		<question id="21" multiple="1">
			<direction>One reason why Spiros felt happy about his marketing presentation was that</direction>
			<a>he was not nervous.</a>
			<b>his style was good.</b>
			<c>the presentation was the best in his group.</c>
		</question>
		<question id="22" multiple="1" dir="5">
			<description>What surprised Hiroko about the other students&#39; presentations?</description>
			<a>Their presentations were not interesting.</a>
			<b>They found their presentations stressful.</b>
			<c>They didn&#39;t look at the audience enough.</c>
		</question>
		<question id="23" multiple="1" dir="5">
			<description>After she gave her presentation, Hiroko felt</description>
			<a>delighted.</a>
			<b>dissatisfied.</b>
			<c>embarrassed.</c>
		</question>
		<question id="24" multiple="1" dir="5">
			<description>How does Spiros feel about his performance in tutorials?</description>
			<a>not very happy</a>
			<b>really pleased</b>
			<c>fairly confident</c>
		</question>
		<question id="25" multiple="1" dir="5">
			<description>Why can the other students participate so easily in discussions?</description>
			<a>They are polite to each other.</a>
			<b>They agree to take turns in speaking.</b>
			<c>They know each other well.</c>
		</question>
		<question id="26" multiple="1" dir="5">
			<description>Why is Hiroko feeling more positive about tutorials now?</description>
			<a>She finds the other students&#39; opinions more interesting.</a>
			<b>She is making more of a contribution.</b>
			<c>The tutor includes her in the discussion.</c>
		</question>
		<question id="27" multiple="1" dir="5">
			<description>To help her understand lectures, Hiroko</description>
			<a>consulted reference materials.</a>
			<b>had extra tutorials with her lecturers.</b>
			<c>borrowed lecture notes from other students.</c>
		</question>
		<question id="28" multiple="1" dir="5">
			<description>What does Spiros think of his reading skills?</description>
			<a>He reads faster than he used to.</a>
			<b>It still takes him a long time to read.</b>
			<c>He tends to struggle with new vocabulary.</c>
		</question>
		<question id="29" multiple="1" dir="5">
			<description>What is Hiroko&#39;s subject area?</description>
			<a>environmental studies</a>
			<b>health education</b>
			<c>engineering</c>
		</question>
		<question id="30" multiple="1" dir="5">
			<description>Hiroko thinks that in the reading classes the students should</description>
			<a>learn more vocabulary.</a>
			<b>read more in their own subject areas.</b>
			<c>develop better reading strategies.</c>
		</question>
	
		<question id="31" multiple="0" qty="10" dir="6">
			<![CDATA[
			<h2>Mass Strandings of Whales and Dolphins</h2>
			Mass strandings: situations where groups of whales, dolphins, etc. swim onto the beach
			and die<br />
			Common in areas where the <b>31</b><div id="ques31" class="questext"></div> can change quickly<br />
			Several other theories:<br />
			<br />
			<b>Parasites</b><br />
			e.g. some parasites can affect marine animals&#39; <b>32</b><div id="ques32" class="questext"></div>, which they depend on for navigation<br />
			<br />
			<b>Toxins</b><br />
			Poisons from <b>33</b><div id="ques33" class="questext"></div> or <div id="ques33" class="questext"></div> are commonly consumed by whales<br />
			e.g. Cape Cod (1988) &#8211; whales were killed by saxitoxin<br />
			<br />
			<b>Accidental  Strandings</b><br />
			Animals may follow prey ashore, e.g. Thurston (1995)<br />
			Unlikely because the majority of animals were not <b>34</b><div id="ques34" class="questext"></div> when they stranded<br />
			<br />
			<b>Human Activity</b><br />
			<b>35</b><div id="ques35" class="questext"></div>from military tests are linked to some recent strandings<br />
			The Bahamas (2000) stranding was unusual because the whales<br />
			<ul>
				<li>were all <b>36</b><div id="ques36" class="questext"></div></li>
				<li>were not in a <b>37</b><div id="ques37" class="questext"></div></li>
			</ul>
			<br />
			<b>Group Behaviour</b><br />
			<ul>
				<li>More strandings in the most <b>38</b><div id="ques38" class="questext"></div> species of whales</li>
				<li>1994 dolphin stranding &#8211; only the <b>39</b><div id="ques39" class="questext"></div> was ill</li>
			</ul>
			<br />
			<b>Further Reading</b><br />
			Marine Mammals Ashore (Connor) &#8211; gives information about stranding <b>40</b><div id="ques40" class="questext"></div>.
			]]>
		</question>
	</questions>
</listening>

<reading>
	<passage1>
		<direction>
			<![CDATA[
			<i>You should spend about 20 minutes on <b>Questions 1-13</b>,  which are based on Reading Passage 1 on pages 2 and 3.</i>
			]]>
		</direction>
		<question>
			<![CDATA[
			<h2>William Henry Perkin</h2>
			<h4>The man who invented synthetic dyes</h4>
			<p>William Henry Perkin was born on March 12, 1838, in London, England. As a boy, Perkin&#39;s curiosity prompted early interests in the arts, sciences, photography, and engineering. But it was a chance stumbling upon a run-down, yet functional, laboratory in his late grandfather&#39;s home that solidified the young man&#39;s enthusiasm for chemistry.</p>
			<p>As a student at the City of London School, Perkin became immersed in the study of chemistry. His talent and devotion to the subject were perceived by his teacher, Thomas Hall, who encouraged him to attend a series of lectures given by the eminent scientist Michael Faraday at the Royal Institution. Those speeches fired the young chemist&#39;s enthusiasm further, and he later went on to attend the Royal College of Chemistry, which he succeeded in entering in 1853, at the age of 15.</p>
			<p>At the time of Perkin&#39;s enrolment, the Royal College of Chemistry was headed by the noted German chemist August Wilhelm Hofmann. Perkin&#39;s scientific gifts soon caught Hofmann&#39;s attention and, within two years, he became Hofmann&#39;s youngest assistant. Not long after that, Perkin made the scientific breakthrough that would bring him both fame and fortune.</p>
			<p>At the time, quinine was the only viable medical treatment for malaria. The drug is derived from the bark of the cinchona tree, native to South America, and by 1856 demand for the drug was surpassing the available supply. Thus, when Hofmann made some passing comments about the desirability of a synthetic substitute for quinine, it was unsurprising that his star pupil was moved to take up the challenge.</p>
			<p>During his vacation in 1856, Perkin spent his time in the laboratory on the top floor of his family&#39;s house. He was attempting to manufacture quinine from aniline, an inexpensive and readily available coal tar waste product. Despite his best efforts, however, he did not end up with quinine. Instead, he produced a mysterious dark sludge. Luckily, Perkin&#39;s scientific training and nature prompted him to investigate the substance further. Incorporating potassium dichromate and alcohol into the aniline at various stages of the experimental process, he finally produced a deep purple solution. And, proving the truth of the famous scientist Louis Pasteur&#39;s words &#39;chance favours only the prepared mind&#39;, Perkin saw the potential of his unexpected find.</p>
			<p>Historically, textile dyes were made from such natural sources as plants and animal excretions. Some of these, such as the glandular mucus of snails, were difficult to obtain and outrageously expensive. Indeed, the purple colour extracted from a snail was once so costly that in society at the time only the rich could afford it. Further, natural dyes tended to be muddy in hue and fade quickly. It was against this backdrop that Perkin&#39;s discovery was made.</p>
			<p>Perkin quickly grasped that his purple solution could be used to colour fabric, thus making it the world&#39;s first synthetic dye. Realising the importance of this breakthrough, he lost no time in patenting it. But perhaps the most fascinating of all Perkin&#39;s reactions to his find was his nearly instant recognition that the new dye had commercial possibilities.</p>
			<p>Perkin originally named his dye Tyrian Purple, but it later became commonly known as mauve (from the French for the plant used to make the colour violet). He asked advice of Scottish dye works owner Robert Pullar, who assured him that manufacturing the dye would be well worth it if the colour remained fast (i.e. would not fade) and the cost was relatively low. So, over the fierce objections of his mentor Hofmann, he left college to give birth to the modern chemical industry.</p>
			<p>With the help of his father and brother, Perkin set up a factory not far from London. Utilising the cheap and plentiful coal tar that was an almost unlimited byproduct of London&#39;s gas street lighting, the dye works began producing the world&#39;s first synthetically dyed material in 1857. The company received a commercial boost from the Empress Eug&#233;nie of France, when she decided the new colour flattered her. Very soon, mauve was the necessary shade for all the fashionable ladies in that country. Not to be outdone, England&#39;s Queen Victoria also appeared in public wearing a mauve gown, thus making it all the rage in England as well. The dye was bold and fast, and the public clamoured for more. Perkin went back to the drawing board.</p>
			<p>Although Perkin&#39;s fame was achieved and fortune assured by his first discovery, the chemist continued his research. Among other dyes he developed and introduced were aniline red (1859) and aniline black (1863) and, in the late 1860s, Perkin&#39;s green. It is important to note that Perkin&#39;s synthetic dye discoveries had outcomes far beyond the merely decorative. The dyes also became vital to medical research in many ways. For instance, they were used to stain previously invisible microbes and bacteria, allowing researchers to identify such bacilli as tuberculosis, cholera, and anthrax. Artificial dyes continue to play a crucial role today. And, in what would have been particularly pleasing to Perkin, their current use is in the search for a vaccine against malaria.</p>
			<i>Questions 1 &#8211; 7<br />
			Do the following statements agree with the information given in Reading Passage 1?<br />
			In boxes 1-7 on your answer sheet, write<br />
			<b>TRUE</b> if  the statement agrees with the information<br />
			<b>FALSE</b> if  the statement contradicts the information<br />
			<b>NOT GIVEN</b> if  there is no information on this</i><br />
			<br />
			<b>1</b> Michael Faraday was the first person to recognise Perkin&#39;s ability as a student of chemistry.<br /><div id="ques1"></div><br />
			<b>2</b> Michael Faraday suggested Perkin should enrol in the Royal College of Chemistry.<br /><div id="ques2"></div><br />
			<b>3</b> Perkin employed August Wilhelm Hofmann as his assistant.<br /><div id="ques3"></div><br />
			<b>4</b> Perkin was still young when he made the discovery that made him rich and famous.<br /><div id="ques4"></div><br />
			<b>5</b> The trees from which quinine is derived grow only in South America.<br /><div id="ques5"></div><br />
			<b>6</b> Perkin hoped to manufacture a drug from a coal tar waste product.<br /><div id="ques6"></div><br />
			<b>7</b> Perkin was inspired by the discoveries of the famous scientist Louis Pasteur.<br /><div id="ques7"></div><br />
			<br />
			<i>Questions 8 &#8211; 13<br />
			Answer the questions below.<br />
			Choose <b>NO MORE THAN TWO WORDS</b> from the passage for each answer.<br />
			Write your answers in boxes 8-13 on your answer sheet.</i><br />
			<br />
			<b>8</b> Before Perkin&#39; discovery, with what group in society was the colour purple associated?<br /><div id="ques8"></div><br />
			<b>9</b> What potential did Perkin immediately understand that his new dye had?<br /><div id="ques9"></div><br />
			<b>10</b> What was the name finally used to refer to the first colour Perkin invented?<br /><div id="ques10"></div><br />
			<b>11</b> What was the name of the person Perkin consulted before setting up his own dye works?<br /><div id="ques11"></div><br />
			<b>12</b> In what country did Perkin&#39;s newly invented colour first become fashionable?<br /><div id="ques12"></div><br />
			<b>13</b> According to the passage, which disease is now being targeted by researchers using synthetic dyes?<br /><div id="ques13"></div>
			]]>
		</question>
	</passage1>
</reading>
</content>
</ielts>